hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream
66.2 on February 15
2024 we're very much looking forward to
this followup on a very delightful
66.1 so thank you Susan Hasty for
organizing and helping with this to you
for the introduction
oh unmute and continue thank
you okay thank you Daniel um and thank
you Adrien for coming back um last uh
our last session we covered design in
nature your book on design in nature and
um and this is my favorite book of all
which is what we're going to cover today
um which is evolution and freedom so I'm
going to turn it over to you and I look
forward to this presentation and our
discussion
afterwards okay thank you for the
invitation uh especially uh in view of
the fact that this is my second um um uh
appearance on your um um
show um the um the written version of uh
of our discussion is in this book which
is still relatively
fresh and um I prepared a few slides for
the next 20 or 25 minutes uh the first
slides are A Brief Review of my previous
um presentation which is about the fact
that uh the phenomenon that um screams
to be
recognized uh in nature or for that
matter in physics is the um uh
appearance and then the evolution of the
flow
configuration the flow configuration as
you can see here unites the animate with
the inanimate in other words it does
away with the dichotomy inherited from
the church and with that idea going
forward everything that flows and moves
on Earth is driven by um by a power
which comes from the consumption of fuel
and food um and there flow
architectures most of them natural that
function as engines for example the the
atmosphere the hydrosphere all these
things that move are driven by power and
as they as they move and as they morph
they dissipate the power and I call the
dissipated features
brakes and on the right hand side you
see a summary of everything uh which
means the Geo the bio and the socio are
of morphing meaning evolving flow
architectures the um the statement that
emerges after all these observations
again it's based on observations in
other words this law of evolution in
nature is of empirical origin like all
of laws of physics and um and um it says
that it actually defines the life state
which is our subject today for for a
flow system to persist in time it must
evolve with freedom such that it
provides greater access so the
phenomenon is the evolution of flowing
form uh which is actually the time Arrow
or the definition of future as something
different than the present and the
past the keywords are only two the ones
that will um give us support in the
conversation so uh the the definition of
Evolution from the dictionary is changes
that occur in a discernable Direction in
time um that direction is known by many
names objective purpose go there are
many other such words that uh that
represent Common Sense Common Sense
Freedom uh are physical features that
allow an entity we call that system and
theonomics to exhibit changes um Freedom
can be measured in terms of the number
of degrees of freedom for example uh the
Piston moving in and out of the cylinder
of the engine has one degree of Freedom
which is the position of the Piston um
other uh configurations the natural ones
have innumerable degrees of freedom you
can look at the direction in which your
cat is uh is moving and um and anyway
the freedom description is a very very
thick book of
examples uh the pun sign is that without
this physical feature called Freedom uh
there can be no Evolution and no design
and for that matter no no direction in
time uh the book has 11 chapters uh time
is short so I will if I'm lucky I'll
I'll touch on the the the chapters
lighted in red and I'll take take them
one at a time economies of scale is an
observation from economics uh coming
from um uh design in nature this
observation is predictable uh in the
upper left hand corner uh this is a
classroom exercise you can show easily
that if a stream a stream of a
particular flow rate
flows through two parallel tubes meaning
one stream divided to flow in parallel
through those two tubes that stream
flows a lot easier through a single tube
with a with a flow volume equal to the
sum of the previous two um in the um
second example um if the flow is
external to the uh to the solid walls
that is for example in two barges that
are pulled up The River by um by two TG
boats well um the load the total load on
those two barges is pulled a lot easier
on a single barge that's bigger so in
going from left to right in both
examples from left to right it is easier
to go from two to one and that according
to Constructor law direction of
evolution from 2 to one um uh suggests
that these two examples the uh uh the
phenomenon of of accretion or Confluence
or Association is uh is part of nature
if that is so then why is it that the
flows everywhere around us are not of
one big size and the reason is that the
flows on areas and inside of volume such
as the animal body are flows between one
point in an area and one point in and a
volume in other words flows between one
point and very very very many points and
this kind of um uh let's call it design
challenge is U is satisfied or answered
by a flow architecture called
hierarchy and uh again empirically
hierarchies are everywhere but those who
are curious can discover them um one by
one and report them in ways that are
memorable and the easiest to me memorize
a a punchline is to arrive at the same P
punch line many times in presumably
disconnected domains so here in in
Social organization the uh the um
hierarchy of cities in Europe plotted on
the on the vertical versus the city rank
clearly the big cities are very few the
biggest one is only one and then these
descending lines best known empirically
as zip distributions are um proceeding
the same way with a uh with a relatively
fixed slope um over time the lines move
upward because population has been
increasing but the um the hierarchy
Remains the Same the zigzag line at the
very top is a uh is a prediction of this
descending uh Trend one based on a very
simple model that I use in my classroom
from cities in Europe to trees in the
forest um this is a you see this uh uh
these this air these two areas that
occupy the descending diagonal they
represent that
based on
assuming several patterns of
distribution of tre canopies on the
forest floor these are three canopies
seen from above uh Bas regardless of
what pattern of construction you choose
the hierarchy is uh is relatively rigid
and it looks just like the hierarchy of
cities distributed over a
continent uh here is another example uh
this is is in fact a um an icon of the
distribution of animal populations on
the globe uh population size versus body
size it is a descending um
Association um which if one gets really
curious could punctuate with actual data
from the zoology literature clearly
we're familiar with aircraft uh
airplanes uh
are falling on the same line and the P
line is that the hierarchy is natural
and um and uh the one size is not so uh
that's a very important line to keep in
mind as we um as we I don't know what I
did that I lost my
um oh my
God I cannot change the slide though
right what am I
doing uh
[Music]
um here we go so now I get to the next
uh next topic
inequality um here's the movement the
actual movement on the area um most
familiar to us is the movement of
freight um it is on an area it has many
participants but uh the few the few are
large big uh they travel fast and they
travel long uh the same Freight is uh is
carried by a multitude of smaller
Vehicles traveling uh slowly and short
distances uh the freight is one the
freight is the one that scans the area
and uh this coexistence of of the few
with the many is is in a is stable it is
in a stasis stasis it is harmonious
um in the animal realm is the same story
you see down down the slide the the
coexistence of the
few large and long and fast with the
with the prey that move short slow and
the prey is very
numerous uh which is a um coexistence
that does not change over time uh now in
the human realm we
Also let's say in our in our lifetime uh
the hierarchy of movement on the globe
it is in this case represented by
Aviation uh the color red is
about high
density U movement of people people were
flying carpets called airplanes and um
the rest of the globe is All In Motion
it is interconnected
but sooner or later
uh individuals from the Blue Area have
access to other points in the blue area
by passing through the two chambers of
the heart of world Aviation so uh
incidentally hierarchy in movement is
synonymous with hierarchy in the
consumption of fuel and what you see on
the image has emerged naturally it is
not the result a dictate from say the
United
Nations uh now on the left side we
learned that the hierarchy in movement
and fuel use is synonymous with the
hierarchy in the distribution of Freedom
not of of wealth not Freedom wealth on
the left side data from from economics
uh show the coincidence that um if you
plot the wealth on the vertical and the
consumption of fuel on the horizontal
the um populations of the world fall on
the diagonal so uh I regard this um uh
first graph on the left side as a an
entry in a dictionary which explains
that what is known as wealth
distribution in economics is known as
the consumption of of fuel or for that
matter the the distribution of of human
movement in engineering and in physics
and um social dynamics on the right hand
side the same data are plotted with the
fuel use on the on the vertical and
economic freedom on the horizontal and
uh the arrow pointing toward the future
because by the way all these dots are
racing upward meaning listen to mental
reports they all are about uh this year
being better than last year I mean if if
the people get lucky then on the right
hand side you see that the dots
are the dots are M migrating toward um
toward the greater Freedom uh this is
obvious graphically but no not known
very well um uh to the to the Bro to the
to the general
public now uh looking more closely at
what's going on uh in every such country
Advanced or not so Advanced the
population uh has uh unequal uh access
to to wealth and um uh this is a common
uh presentation of the distribution of
wealth in society on the in on the
vertical direction is the
the um um accumulated share of income
that is a share that that belongs to a
partic fraction of the population so the
income share is called Epsilon the
fraction of the population is beta we'll
see this graph more than once after this
and if the distribution of income were
to be uniform over the population then
the curve should be the straight
diagonal
but none of the curves are straight they
are in fact
convex with say France and Germany being
relatively close to the
diagonal uh the US and China
uh although similar to each other
they're uh more convex and uh brazili
and South Africa arguably less developed
than the previous four um have curves
that are even more convex meaning devia
deviating from the
diagonal um we're going to see very soon
why uh this uh convex curve is
natural um and um I decided to
illustrate or to present the answer by
imagining a population unlike in this
graph about the four six countries a
population of things that are not do not
represent uh human society and um I have
on the left side images of the so-called
river basins beginning with the uh
actual river River delta then the River
Basin of air flow through the lungs uh
River Basin of water uh being pumped up
upward by the the tree in in Africa and
then in the bottom photograph the River
Basin of skars coming down the slope
toward the Chalet um they're all
hierarchical and their convex curves
convex curves are crowded in the lower
left corner of the Epsilon versus beta
graph in other words by the way the the
rest of the picture shows details of
that
crowdedness for the details you have to
flip through the book the point is that
in the absence of people in the
population on this flowing system the um
the inequality is U is uh much much much
worse so uh uh social existence meaning
uh living together has brought these
curves upward from the lower right
corner uh in the direction of the
diagonal this uh this is in my opinion
good news but it is relatively unknown
In the comparison between the living
society and the by the way they're all
life FL systems but the comparison
between a human society and a society of
things that flow without people
connected to their neighbors is that
difference is is the
Striking this brings me to two examples
of social organization and how it
benefits from in Innovation the first
example is a look at the prehistory from
left to right on the in the vertical
direction that the Q represents in
dimensional terms represents the the
rate of U of um um loss of heating from
a uh container with hot water hot water
being used by primitive uh population on
the abissa that's the horizontal
direction is that m TAA is dimensionless
and is proportional to the rate of hot
water
consumption by indivi by one individual
it means that on the
Absa the direction of time from
prehistory to modern times is from left
to right now if you look at the
piecewise linear curve that emerges it
starts on the left with um with the the
um hunting and Gathering individuals
living in in Huts one pot of hot water
meaning on fire for one particular Hut
and that pot leaks heat to the ambient
and that rate of heat leak is
proportional to the Q on the
ordinate um now the invention the first
one is uh where was the idea of having a
larger pot of the hot water um as shown
in the example called n equals 3 and
then from that pot the individuals are
drawing their own supply of of hot water
and then climbing up the curve one
invention after the next leads to social
organization or leads to Association
more more individuals or more neighbors
uh come com together and benefiting from
one Central uh uh source of hot water
and what's interesting here is that the
um from one invention to the next the
slope of the curve uh decreases and that
means that on a per individual basis it
becomes less uh uh uh costly or uh the
loss diminishes and therefore
everything about hot water becomes more
economical the next
graph is about another invention called
the dendritic design as opposed to
radial design so the dendritic design um
is a an invention that allows the user
to to get by with by paying even less
for uh heat loss to the ambient in other
words the the making of hot water B
becomes more economical the radial
designs envelope is at the top and you
see these thin lines uh they have to do
with the invention um and the the thin
lines are uh descending they are sliding
downward as the size of the population
called the capital L
increases a second example of uh uh what
an invention does uh for the benefit of
the whole population is here um I
proposed this uh uh image of of complete
complete equality
um of a
population um it's spelled out at the
top you have a square domain populated
with equal inhabitants equal inputs of
something for example water or hot water
or whatever uh milk if you want uh and
equal channels um and equal channels are
bathed by equal flow rates and this is
this area is a um an area that
facilitates the flow of this something
from the area to the point and the point
call The Source or the the sink is in
the lower right corner um
and going from the upper right to the
lower left the um the grid becomes finer
which means that the population
increases on the Square and um in that
direction the um the convex curve of
Epsilon versus
beta migrates toward the corner in the
lower right in other words the
distribution of this flow over the pop
population becomes less and less
equal um and that direction is the
direction of the increase in the popula
the size of the
population um so this is the first
conclusion uh next is what can be done
about it um and by the way U you may
have thought of Communism if you look at
the first paragraph um the this imposed
equality on on the population is uh is
easy to imagine
maybe kind of more difficult to
implement but that has been tried but
when there's movement from the area to
one point sorcery sync uh clearly
clearly the individual um in the
vicinity of that very special Point
benefits from a bigger beta a bigger
beta U corresponding to anyway very few
people like himself or herself anyway
what can be done about it so assume that
the design has only two * two
participants as in the upper right that
simplest square and that simple square
is investigated here first um it is
reproduced in the lower right corner and
it's labeled a design without innovation
um to to the left there are two designs
in which one Innovation was implemented
and that Innovation is represented by
the solid Arrow the solid arrow is the
idea of somebody to reduce the flow
resistance between two neighbors so um
in other words the flow was liberated by
um by one
inventor uh with regard to his or her
access to uh an adjacent neighbor and
you see here that um uh regardless of
where this inventor was located on the
Square the effect of liberating the flow
is to move the curve that curve to move
it closer to the to the diagonal so uh a
single Innovation is a local design
change that uh benefits uh
the entire population not only the
inventor
um next uh again all these examples have
to do with changes changes that happen
in in uh flow rates and the distribution
of flow rates called movement and wealth
and all these other things including
Freedom over the population another way
to characterize all these things the
hierarchy and the inequality and so on
uh is the word diversity and here I um
show several images of diversity in what
con concerns us the most which is Human
Society uh this is my um um graphic way
of of putting in front of you where the
homo sapiens came from um this is a
picture of the
past two or three millennia
um it it began with Theus and
then the spread the first migration was
uh 2 million years ago uh the next uh
the ,000 den was 500,000 years ago um
and then the rest you can leave the
labels on the uh on this uh on this uh
Fork shaped flow architecture what I
think you should pay attention to is the
the word artifact which is in the red at
the very top all this movement uh
movement toward the uh div
diversification of the of the population
of homo sapiens had to do with with
change change which means if you want
inventions uh on the on the obsa on the
timeline fire fire was an add-on that um
empowered the prehistoric human next and
the fire when because of fire the first
migration Out of Africa became possible
next came clothing clothing made the
second migration possible clearly in the
direction of of North and Northeast uh
Europe and um Eurasia
Siberia uh clothing big deal uh fire and
clothing
both have to do with power power and the
heating or the retention of of that
heating and then the third um power
related change or artifact was boating
boating which
enabled uh these early humans and
hominids to uh to invade the the world
of the world as we know it the result as
you see the horizontal line
is the diverse population that
characterizes
uh the globe today and now all that
means that the mod modern humans
are the object of the history that is
taught in schools that history
is only the blink of one eye 10,000
years um no more and in this direction
more of the same took place you look at
these artifacts on the timeline at the
very bottom agriculture the wheel
domesticated animals and then of course
the uh the mechanism the machines
language of course and literature uh
printing press and all today all the way
to today's uh advancements in human
affluence which are in fact possible
because of the Industrial
Revolution um and now U coming even
closer to who we are and closer to the
present science itself is an
evolutionary design that um that um took
place and continues to take place
because of freedom freedom to uh inov
innovate freedom to communicate and
freedom to implement my own special is
thermodynamics um this is relatively new
science 50 years since it it started to
spread seriously before theonomics the
science had very strong legs uh all of
them successful uh the heating part was
called caloric Theory uh the rest of it
without heating was called mechanics
this is as old as as even before the
Greeks the old Greeks and of course uh
Evolution which really means design is
also even older than the previous too we
see it in in everything from cave
paintings to to the Renaissance and of
course uh uh the kind of U you know uh
designing and the construction that's
going on today along the way the science
the science became unified uh with a
construct the law uh the branch called
the heat transer where um thermal
engineering joined the rest of the uh
the uh the the theory and became uh what
I'm what I'm teaching today and what I
think is very very powerful science of
theonomics with uh design evolution in
it so um where is this uh uh arrow
pointing obviously it's pointing toward
the future the um but the present
unfortunately is a little bit
complicated um let me go back to the
previous story if you read any book of
the history of physics or the history of
theonomics you'll find um a story about
individuals the uh the very few the very
few beginning with Sadi Carno and his
father was called named Lazar Caro um
before that of course Archimedes and
many many of these very very few uh
distinguishable names um and um design
Evolution has its own luminaries
individuals individuals who um lived and
uh created in places that were known
known for uh creativity and for the uh
for the sanctity of the
individual uh places geographically but
also places in the history of the human
civilization uh the names of these
individuals uh speak of uh who they were
where they lived and what language they
spoke well um less and less of that is
uh is uh is the character of what goes
on today in science this is a cartoon
from the very popular French magazine
called po
Lans uh which is
something like between American
scientist and the uh Scientific American
you see here um yeah a joke about uh
what you what you see published these
days articles coauthored by uh 10 or 20
or sometimes 40 co-authors 40
co-authors um which give the impression
or attemp to perpetuate the uh the The
View that better science comes from the
larger group uh that is a view that's
not original uh it happened with the
collectivization of Agriculture and um
the history of the 20th century is very
clear about the uh the uh
the the success of that success in
quotation marks well um uh this is the
present and luckily in it uh this is
what's going on in it there are
individuals just like in the books of uh
of of the history of of science uh who
by their very nature um do not feel at
home um uh Marching In
colums they simply run away if they can
survive or they shy away uh they the
they are not
joiners they are happy with their
ideas because uh only that way uh they
can uh climb paks unlike the margin
columns so I end with uh the view of
this little man conquering Mount Everest
I drew I made a drawing in 1975 with a
big pen in one stroke um 1975 is when I
was uh uh leaving uh MIT to become a
post do in Berkeley uh and I uh I that
that uh caricature is Adrian um
attracted by by the idea somewhere at
the very top and this is on the left uh
uh how it how it looks from that very
high position uh the single
investigator the one with the driven by
ideas uh does two things and both are uh
comforting one is uh
he steps on Deadwood Deadwood that's a
metaphor for everything from old ideas
and inactive or groups that are not
creative but in front of the individual
there is a an infinite uh Blue Sky of
opportunity in which the ideas could be
projected tried and
implemented so this is the thread of the
book once again on the right hand side
and thank you for your
attention thank you thank you Adrian
should I stop sharing
um you can leave it okay Susan would you
like to
begin sure yes
sure um so what I'd like to do is is is
kind of share some insights that um that
have occurred to me me and you get you
Daniel and you Adrien um of whether you
know I'm I'm on the
evolutionary track right or you or it'll
give us something to riff about um um so
as I reread this and I have a an
autograph copy here um it really the
impact became much more powerful for me
because one I started understanding that
there's a correlation now there's a
difference in the language here but
there's a correlation Daniel um that um
active what Constructor law does is
actually
validate um active inference because
what Constructor law is saying is that
you nature is going to evolve um based
on minimizing heat transfer or heat loss
and free energy is saying the same thing
with you know we are driven to um
minimize our free
energy oh no no no no okay so so so hold
on a yeah said that yeah I know that
these are two different terms but I'm
I'm just trying to connect this for the
audience um and um and so I have some
really specific questions for you so I
want to I want to kind of stay stay on
back here not get caught up in in too
much of the definitions because one is
the audience that's going to watch this
they're probably not going to be as um
astute about the the hard science of
thermodynamics um versus you know the uh
the machine learning the um the biology
the psychology the philosophy that you
know that we really talk about here so
I'm just kind of threading that need
need um just so when I when I kind of
start C start trying to capture the
essence of the beauty quite frankly of
the Constructor law they're able to
connect those those blankets okay um
okay let me let me let me respond to
what you bring up Okay I uh I think more
highly of the audience I think the
audience
is stood and even even if even those
like Adrian who are not experts in a
particular uh corner of science are able
to connect the dots and this is why um U
my way of teaching is to use um common
language whenever uh whenever possible
uh and that is the direction in which I
I want to to push our dialogue here uh I
want to I want to respond to a few
things that you said first uh design in
nature evolution is not about minimizing
heat loss it is about providing uh
meaning evolutionary design changing
design morphing design uh to u to
facilitate uh flow or movement and in
every uh example of mine um the uh the
Mover the Mover the answer to the
question what moves was the IND idual or
the group any yes the individual which
is why I started with hunting and
Gathering benefited as a mover meaning
as a living uh body benefited from uh
not wasting U uh heat from the pot of
hot water okay meaning the individual
benefited from being economical here you
see the word being economical or being
Thrifty as another way of expressing the
natural tendency uh encapsulated in the
Constructor law so that that is that is
that is the that is design in nature
second design in nature has nothing to
do with what you call free energy it is
about it is about this moving
architecture that keeps on changing and
yes uh in order to move the object I
call it theonomic system the The Entity
must be pushed and the pushing comes
from power and the power comes from uh
architectures most of them natural some
a few of them made by people called
engines were functioning as engines what
those systems consume uh from animals to
uh to uh to people and to the entire
Globe um are called food fuel and solar
U solar input um that is uh and and
those things those things are not free
those things are not free uh I can give
you examples of how dear every single
one is uh and finally finally um you and
I had a conversation via email if the
audience would like to find out what
free energy means I would be happy to
come back and give you uh again common
common sense uh or uh common language uh
presentation of what is meant by free
energy in
thermodynamics um it is a pretty good
name for something that was
coin around 1860
1860 but no free energy is not free okay
and and it is not responsible for
setting things in motion or for creating
change changes quite the opposite free
energy is a is a um just like entropy
mathematical formula uh useful in the
description of a of a of an entity that
is in perfect equilibrium with its
environment in other words an entity
that is not pushed by the surroundings
or pushing the surroundings uh but it is
useful for for other reasons which
require a hourong
discussion um and yes some illustration
that I offer to to produce if if people
are curious uh but by the way U I'm not
criticizing anybody and certainly uh
free energy principle is something else
not free energy okay so that's the uh
keep in mind these are two different
Notions and uh but it's very important
to to to to be very clear about one
about the the fact that in our
conversation we uh we respect the
meaning of the
words absolutely and thank you for that
because I mean that actually
um Rich enriched my uh the how I'm tying
or banding these together I kind of like
to point to the economical because that
actually makes a lot of sense
but in reading the book what I did get a
distinction of and again you I want to
hear correct me that's not a problem is
that you know when we're thinking about
active inference and you you know we're
really more focused on you the agents
and the and interactions with the agents
and what I what I um what occurred to me
especially as I was looking through your
slides Adrian is you know is that the
flow architecture um one it's it's kind
of pointing us toward what is actually
flowing and so many of our mental models
are static so this is where I think that
it you do have to really wrestle with
this but understanding how nature is um
is designing and cesing um and how we as
interactive agents in these flow
architectures are um are reacting to the
um the the natural things I mean in
other words in in in condensing the
information I was like okay the flow
architecture is the natural things that
are observable palatable movable and
measurable okay um and um and the the
flow Direction and the
configuration and the time I.E rhythm
is actually what is what needs to be
free um and and I pulled one thing that
I thought was really rich in terms of um
these features which again are
contextually bound but they're flowing
together and one point I wanted to make
was is that they have to be or or ask
you about in terms of how are those
features needing to be independent
first and number two is um is how they
are flowing together you pointed at it
in one of the slides here but the how
they're actually more economical when
they are powering
together well I think is a you a really
key key aspect here let me let me
respond it is uh
it I confess early on
that's 25 years ago um coming from
engineering i u i saw I saw flow first
before I saw the configuration or the
design flowing or changing or morphing
the phenomenon is uh is not the the flow
and the direction or for that matter the
uh the decrease in the so-called flow
resistance the phenomenon is the um the
um um tendency of the um of the design
to change all of it to change so that so
that that movement which is belongs to
the body but also to the niche around it
that movement is
facilitated um a friend of mine the
other day brought up the example of the
U one of the valves moving and flapping
inside the human heart
uh yes that is the valve is the niche
the flow is the blood flow the blood
flow has edies the blood flow is
constantly morphing keep in mind the the
flow of liquid is uh is uh is
complicated it's like stuffing a rope
down the throat of a gun barrel it's a
it's it has configuration that's
invisible to to most Mortals and in a
case of the uh of of the living organ
the heart uh the stuffing of the Rope
called blood flow uh brings with it the
uh the rhythmic the loving uh
deformation of the of the flap of the
valve and U and this is all for the
benefit of the moving animal yes the
freedom and the the life I call it
access according to construct the law uh
the freedom is freedom Galore in the
description of what I just told you
there are inumerable degrees of freedom
you know the bending of the of the flap
the direction of the flap the rhythm of
the flap and that's only about the flap
but when I get into the edes inside the
blood flow well those are innumerable
once again hierarchical a few large and
many small and they move these blobs
moving speak of Rhythm but if you take a
snapshot you see hierarchy uh yes it's
complicated but it happened naturally uh
and the direction of the happening is
toward making a better and better animal
a a longer living animal a longer
traveling animal that is the uh the and
and why should the animal evolve in that
direction because the animal along with
with with the with his or her
compatriots but is a participant in the
River Basin of water called Humanity
humanity is spining water on the globe
and morphing and evolving and getting
okay better at moving itself which means
moving water just like any River Basin
or just like the hydrosphere and uh it's
all a relatively boring conclusion
because it's always the same conclusion
but it is a beautiful conclusion because
it makes us on the one hand not waste
time on something that repeats itself
and gives us the opportunity to come up
with with better ideas or new ideas or
frankly to make D big biger noise to say
aha Aha and I'll say another thing
before I stop
um you brought up more freedom yes it's
very important in um in my okay modest
way of teaching these things I show what
happens if you have a one of these
morphing designs uh U any anything such
as a very simple drawing of of a River
Basin and what happens if you uh uh
increase the number of degrees of
freedom from one one version
design to the next so I show this is
with pencil and paper that as the number
of degrees of freedom increases the
access which is measured in many ways um
access increases if What flows is people
walking through the streets and
everything including vehicles that means
wealth increases uh in the direction of
Greater freedom and this is why it's no
it's no coincidence no coincidence that
that the distribution of innovation on
the globe is uh is nonuniform nonuniform
just as non-uniform in fact it co
coincides with the nonuniform
distribution of wealth wealth and the
consumption of fuel and all these other
things that are that are
undeniable so this is the coincidence to
keep in mind and keep it in mind when
you hear people calling for uh uniform
distribution of this and uniform
distribution of that and for certain
groups to cut down in the consumption of
fuel and to stop using you know
commercial Aviation because they are
burning too much fuel yeah think about
that think about how intelligent that
the proposal would be and by the way uh
the reason is not intelligent is because
even if if you implement it it is
calling to be replaced tomorrow because
that kind of change is unnatural you
see I'm not okay so um so here's where
I'm confused
um and so help me help me to kind of
pull this together because we talk a lot
about um about self organizing systems
and and about degrees of freedom and
what I'm kind of teasing out and you
maybe I'm confused maybe not but you
what I'm as I'm digging into this and
really you appreciating the richness of
of your Precision of your language um I
want to I want to kind of capitalize on
um on as as the evolution occurs um and
um and
how going back to the inequality and how
the system is natural natur Al going to
lead to the different the different
areas and volumes that the point of the
area and the volume I think is I think
that's one of the richest things that
probably the hardest to grasp in here
but but yeah but the also the more
volume there is and this is a question
um then the more um coalescence the um
uh accretion I believe is increases but
that also leads to
fragmentation is that how does that
relate to the the point in the area let
me let me address that you this big
volume you referred to um is one um one
feature of the object or of the design
is called size size everything that we
uh use in our discussion today is about
the a thing with many features including
size size is a natural feature uh I I
started that way not not not everything
is big or not everything is should be
this small yeah everything should be
this size and if you if you look
carefully at the at the literature That
Grew around the construct law you'll see
many
many predictions of what the size of the
bird should be the size of this airplane
should be and the size of this
helicopter should be because size is a a
natural feature of the moving flow
system and U so uh what moves is uh
is
a more complicated story than acre
accretion is comes from celestial bodies
where where let's say particles in the
primordial soup attract each other and
they come together or forget about the
uh the uh the thing that nobody saw
nobody saw the primordial soup but you
can look at you can no you can
actually look at uh at the little uh
suspensions of dust and how they uh they
uh become Aggregates dust Aggregates
shaped as just like the snowflakes
snowflakes uh you see this in Hidden
Corners somewhere in a room where no one
has been for about 30 years uh these
dendrites of of of particles that came
together because of mutual electrostatic
attraction and um yes but well those
systems by this by this time are dead
they are not the object of our our
discussion although on root to those D
rights they were alive and behaving just
like any other any other flow
architecture in their case proceeding
from a volume to one point um so I come
to the um uh anyway the observation is
that the the design in nature is uh is
is not about
uh accretion that's just one one kind of
flow uh it is about uh the the whole
architecture that has this purpose of
enabling uh easier movement for the
whole the whole I think okay what's
difficult here I I recognize where
my
peers feel difficult to grasp the
difficulty is is uh to to get away from
the um from the the present tendency of
of um splitting hairs called U you
know uh respecting too much the infinite
decimal it's called
reductionism uh this discussion about
design in nature is about the whole it's
about the whole uh is about the rising
above uh above the ground and and um and
engage in holism holism and U or getting
away from disciplines and becoming a
polymath okay uh it's about and if you
if you become a polymath you become
closer to being a street person a person
who looks at this poster this poster
reads 10 different books 10 different
books not just narrow narrow narrow
narrow and a person who does not live in
a a in a cubicle or in a locker room a
person who has many friends many friends
a person who knows more than one
language a person yes U this is the the
meaning a truly truly common person and
um that's the invitation to the
scientists is to to to to get out get
out of the department you know
physically or figuratively and smell the
roses uh because beauty beauty is uh
where you don't don't expect to find it
okay meaning it's a it's maybe maybe
behind the house of the neighbor that's
probably where the beauty is
so this one because this one's so rich
but I could go on for hours I'm gonna
turn this back over to
Daniel yeah because thank you so much
because this was been thank you Susan
just in our last minutes um I'll just
add a few small points um first just
beginning with the last common person is
that what is held in Commons a Commons
person and the stewardship of the
commons then in your drawing with the
mountain there was the peak up and there
was the path out and it was like a
person walking on a path forward out in
a river flow and time as you began with
is goal flow it flows in the goal
oriented Direction yes there's more to
it and it's flowing balls roll downhill
and uh the the organism walks forward it
can't walk backwards uh and then the
last point is the uh distributions
empirical that you presented um Jeffrey
West and others have have highlighted
that empirical aspect of the outcomes
and their uh distributions however you
tied that to the
0 to 1 to two to three
dimensional um transfer points where
from one to two is like a point
spreading out on a plate and
threedimensional is like a point
radiating out these are fundamental
equations that are kind of in your
engineering tool kit because they have
to do with like for example heat
distribution but that's just related to
the modes of vibration and the degrees
of freedom of the
molecules as a secondary
distributional approximation to an
actual size specific and that's why
there are river bifurcations that are
this big and not river bifurcations that
are a micron and all these other kinds
of things that are um not just the
neutral we need to explain away about
nature but just straight down the middle
with what the study of nature
is that's right uh yes I couldn't agree
more and I get the I Got U uh
enlightened by by this kind of
commentary um and um and yes you
mentioned Jeffrey West he is one of the
few uh uh in whose company I feel at
home uh they they U it's important it's
important to uh to uh once again to look
at the
uh at life from both sides okay is in
the song uh and um and uh and make a
very strong effort not to become an
ideologue uh um I um I like the opposite
of that which is that uh that
uh my students idea may be better you
see where maybe uh I get corrected every
I teach this course right now I teach it
to a an overflow crowd um and quite
quite frequently uh not every day they
correct me they say how about this and
it's uh it's it's like a free food for
me the sort of
reaction uh uh the listeners should pay
attention I don't get these comments
from my colleagues okay I get them from
these nobody's from these nobody's
called
students
yes don't say that too loud it's a
perfect it's a perfect note and it's one
of the things I've always loved the most
is outside of the organizational
structure and the shape of the building
is about the fact that it's first
principles and about the opportunity
though unlikelihood or not of a
transformative epistemic relationship
across all language and all professional
boundaries so thank you Adrian for for
also living this and sharing how you've
done it
yeah yeah thank you so much this has
been awesome thank you to both of you
till next time bye
bye